Finding Aid for Berenice Bryant Lowe Papers, 1880s-1980s
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Berenice Bryant Lowe Papers
1880s-1980s
Lowe, Berenice Bryant.
Local historian and collector of historical manuscripts. Materials concerning Sojourner Truth, Black abolitionist who settled in Battle Creek, Michigan in 1857; miscellaneous letters of John G. Whittier, George W. Cable; correspondence of Lowe with writer Gerald Carson; diaries of 1963 trip to Europe; and miscellanea and photographs.
851770 Aa 2 Ac
0.8 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came to the library in multiple accessions. Donor no. 3094
The collection is open for research.
Microfilm copy available of Sojourner Truth related items in folders 1-12.
Berenice Lowe (1896-1983) was a local historian and writer from Battle Creek, Michigan. Much of her research was devoted to the life and career of African American abolitionist Sojourner Truth.
The collection consists of two broad groupings of materials: collected articles, photographs, and other information relating to the life of Sojourner Truth; and papers relating to Lowe's various activities and interests, including Battle Creek history and personalities, travel diaries, and her friendship with writer Gerald Carson. In this last grouping of materials are collected letters of others, including autographs and papers of individuals, such as D. J. Van Schnell who wrote to members of the Oldfield family and included with his letters delightful watercolor drawings indicative of English life in the period especially of the late 1930s and the early years of the war.
Most of the Sojourner Truth files have been microfilmed except for a folder of material which came to the library after the 1965 filming. A few photographs that were microfilmed in 1965 were reported missing. These images are only available on the microfilm.
Subjects:
Abolitionists--Michigan--Battle Creek.; African Americans--Michigan.; Antislavery movements--United States.; Authors, American--Michigan.; Battle Creek (Mich.); Lowe, Berenice Bryant.; Truth, Sojourner, d. 1883.; Women abolitionists--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Women--Michigan--Battle Creek.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Delta Chi Fraternity. University of Michigan Chapter.; Phi Kappa Psi. Michigan Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); Triangles (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Junior Hop.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.StudentsSocial life and customs1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.; Truth, Sojourner, d. 1883.
Contributors:
Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925.; Carson, Gerald.; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Sojourner Truth (collected information about)
  - Biographical information compiled by Berenice Lowe (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography
    - Chronology, notes and sources-Hertha Pauli, 10 pages (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography from "Her Name Was Sojourner Truth"-Hertha Pauli (Box 1, Folder 2)
      (missing)
    - "Narrative of Sojourner Truth" letters re from Library of Congress (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Report on National Anti-Slavery Standard (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographies of Sojourner Truth
    - "Truth about Sojourner Truth" written by Berenice Lowe for the Battle Creek Enquirer and News, July 21, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Biographers of Sojourner Truth" written by Berenice Lowe for the Battle Enquirer and News, April 22, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Sojourner Truth, Apostle of Freedom for her Race" article by Forest G. Sweet written for the Battle Creek Sunday Enquirer, Part 1, July 10, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (Part 2; July 17, 1910 is available on microfilm as part of the Willard Library collection)
    - "Sojourner Truth" written by J. H. Brown for the Battle Creek Moon-Journal, April 26, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Lincoln and Sojourner Truth" written by J. H. Brown for the Battle Creek Moon-Journal, May 3, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Sojourner Truth" by George B. Dolliver, written in the "Mainly About Folks" column of the Battle Creek Enquirer and News, March 22, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Phrenological Character of Sojourner Truth" by Nelson Sizer with introduction by Berenice Lowe (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings and reminiscences about Sojourner Truth
    - Information received from Burton Historical Collection about ST, 8 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Typescripts of articles from National Anti-Slavery Standard with introduction, 5 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Typescripts of news items from Battle Creek papers about ST, 13 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Sojourner Truth and Her Birthplace" from The Illustrated American, 1896; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Reminiscence of Henry B. Graves and others about ST (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - News clippings from Detroit Free Press, 1940; 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Obituaries and Tributes
    - Articles from Battle Creek newspapers and from Good Health (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photograph of the grave of ST (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (courtesy of Lou Ryason, Battle Creek Historical Society)
      (negative number na 3027)
  - Book Reviews
    - Reviews of God's Faithful Pilgrim by Arthur H. Fauset (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reviews of Her Name Was Sojourner Truth by Hertha Pauli (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Articles
    - "The Family of Sojourner Truth" article written by Berenice Lowe for Michigan Heritage, III (Summer 1962), 181-185 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper obituaries of Sophia and Thomas Schuyler and Diana Corbin (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper interview with Diana Corbin (daughter of ST) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs and information about paintings of ST
    - Lincoln and Sojourner Truth from a painting by Frank Courter, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (na 3023)
    - Carte de visite photograph of Sojourner Truth (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (used as model by Frank Courter in his painting Lincoln and Sojourner Truth)
      (na 3026)
    - Biography of Courter by Dolliver for "Mainly about Folks" column (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lincoln and Sojourner (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (photograph of painting by Jackson based upon Courter painting)
    - Typescript from Fisk University re Lincoln Bible (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of ST on scrapbook page (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (na 5494; MISSING)
    - Copyprint of ST taken in Detroit (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (MISSING)
    - Photographs of Diana Corbin (two) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Photograph of Frances Titus (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (na 3028)
    - Copy of letter from E. M. Spicer re two painting of ST (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mementoes
    - Lincoln signature and "witness" (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Poster advertising ST lecture (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (na 3029 and na 11855)
    - Photograph of young women in a dress from the Kingman Museum, including comment about the dress (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Book of Life" Scrapbook maintained by ST, Part 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (one of three volumes; a note in the volume indicates that the other two volumes were either lost or destroyed)
    - Message to religious journal from Sojourner Truth, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Songs
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letter from Library of Congress re. songs (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - A hymn to Sojourner and others (Box 1, Folder *)
    - "The Proclamation Day" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sojourner Truth's Church affiliations
    - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Narrative of Sojourner Truth
    - Introduction (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Narrative of Sojourner Truth" by Olive Gilbert, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      (title page and p. 144 containing testimonials; also introduction by Harriet Beecher Stowe)
  - Miscellaneous ST materials, including some photographs added to collection after the initial accession (Box 1, Folder 13)
    (not microfilmed)
- Other materials
  - European diaries, 1963; 4 volumes (Box 1)
  - "Looking Back-Battle Creek", 1969 (Box 1)
    (articles written about Battle Creek history)
  - Gerald Carson, correspondence of BL with, 1955-1972; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters from D. J. Van Schnell to Oldfield family members, 1930s-1940s; 2 folders (Box 2)
    (most of the letters contain small water color drawings reflective of English life and the wartime atmosphere)
  - George Buckley, miscellaneous regarding (Box 2)
  - Re autograph collecting (Box 2)
    (include signed letters from George W. Cable and John G. Whittier)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 2 envelopes; 1 oversize folders (Box 2)
    (include photos of Phi Kappa Psi)
  - Autograph/sentiment book of Susan A. Lapham in which friends contributed poems and sentiments, 1830s (Box 2)